Hi, it's me again.
I'm going to be working with this this other page here.
It's
called time .html because it's dealing
with different functions that operate
using time.
And the first thing is you can see here in my DevTools is we have
this un -caught type error document query selector is no.
So one of the things
that I'm doing in this is I'm I put my script tag in my head,
which is traditionally where they used to be.
But one of the problems is that
the DOM gets read linearly kind of the way that we tend to read.
And so it's actually reading this script tag before
it gets to the body of the HTML. And
so
this div called some stuff.
It says, I'm a div.
When I try to load its text content
here on line 11,
that div doesn't exist yet.
And we could wait like
a hundredth of a second
and it would work.
But
without waiting,
our code doesn't run because it hits this type error and then
and then falls apart.
So I'm going to comment over this console log.
And then I'm going to read through the poem.
And then we're going to let it run.
So I'm opening up these two empty variables here.
Div and internal ID or sorry, interval ID, which
I'll explain in due time.
So the first thing I'm doing is adding
an event listener to the document,
which is the kind of the highest level of the DOM. It's it's actually like everything in the in the page.
And I'm listening for an event called DOM content loaded.
And when DOM content loaded has fired,
then it will run the thing in this nameless function here.
This is not an async function.
This is just a regular function.
So in this,
this is kind of one way to deal with making sure that
everything in the body has loaded that the that the
tags kind of exist as something that you can access.
Another way to do this is to put your script tag below your body.
Right.
But since we're thinking about time in a richer way,
this week, I
thought maybe let's let's actually think about
like the order of events when you load a page.
In a way that gives us some some flexibility.
So within this event listener for DOM content loaded,
it sets div,
which I
put up here.
It's so it's accessible within scope
to things that are below.
So it's setting it to the DOM object,
some stuff,
which says, hi, I'm hypothive.
And then we're doing this.
Do the thing function.
So after it's loaded,
set the set div to point it
that are at our div and then do the thing.
We'll get to do the thing shortly.
It's an async function.
Because I want to be able to do some awaits in it.
But before that, we have this window.
We'll set time out
window in the document are kind of different levels of abstraction.
There are some things that you actually attached
to the window as opposed to the document.
And time outs and intervals are a couple of those things.
So a set time out will run a function.
And you can pass a function that you've written
where you can use a nameless function like this.
After a certain amount of time that's measured in milliseconds.
So in 2.5 seconds.
2,500 milliseconds.
It will do these things.
It will pass the div to the console.
If the div exists because it didn't
without this document add a listener.
And since set this set time out is
actually outside of the event listener,
it's possible that the div will not have loaded yet.
But after 2,500 milliseconds,
it probably will have.
I think if I even set this to 1 millisecond,
it would still work.
And it's going to change the text content
from high-mediv to hello and all caps.
So that's something that will happen after a
certain amount of time of the page loading.
Not from like if I moved this window set time out into
a DOM content loaded,
it would be a little bit slower because it would wait for
the DOM content to have loaded before it set the time out.
But now it's setting the time out right
here in the very early on in the code.
Before I talk about do the thing,
I also want to talk about the sleep
function that I'm using inside of it.
So let me scroll down.
There's some more time outs here.
So the sleep function returns a promise.
We talked about those in the previous demo.
And this promise resolves using a set time out
for an arbitrary number of milliseconds.
So basically what the sleep does is it waits for however many
milliseconds as you pass it and then it returns a promise.
So that's to say,
wait a certain amount of time before you do the next thing.
I also have these functions down here
for start laughing and stop laughing.
You'll remember that I set an interval ID at the top.
And so I call Windows Set Interval.
Set Interval is really similar to set time out
except that it happens over and over and over again.
So Set Interval
is going to take the content of the div and add a hobby for it.
And then it takes,
it adds Ha and then whatever the existing content is.
And it does this every half second,
500 milliseconds.
And then stop laughing.
I write stop on the console.
I change the text content to say and seen to say like,
oh,
this is done.
And I do this window clear interval with the
interval ID that I stored when I started this.
So a set interval will reach,
will reach the end.
And then it turns like to this other variable,
an ID that you can then use to remove it.
Event listeners don't work that way.
I wish they did clearing an invent.
Listeners quite a bit more complicated.
But we don't need to worry about that right now.
So let's go back up to do the thing
and see what's going on here.
The text content is going to be set to waiting five seconds.
And then we sleep for five seconds.
And then another seven seconds,
it sleeps for seven seconds,
seven thousand milliseconds.
At that point, we start laughing.
It's going to start this interval.
Every half a second
of adding Ha. Then I have a for loop here.
And the for loop counts from one
to seven,
because it starts at one.
And it goes to less than eight.
And I set this.
This dur for duration to equal I times a thousand.
So it starts at one.
So it's going to go from one thousand,
two thousand,
three thousand,
four thousand and up.
It's going to change the text content to waiting another.
And then duration milliseconds.
And put a space in here.
Save.
And then it awaits.
To sleep for that long.
So it's waiting longer and longer and longer.
As the as I takes up,
it's that many more thousand milliseconds.
At the end of the loop, it's done looping.
It sleeps for another second and then stops laughing.
So let's see what this does.
Reload this page.
It's waiting five seconds.
Now it says hello.
That's our
set time out up here.
And another seven seconds.
That's down here.
Now it's going to do the loop at the end of that ten.
Seven seconds.
And now it's adding ha ha ha.
We
have our interval running.
We also have our loop running.
These things are kind of overlapping each other in different ways.
So seven thousand milliseconds should be the last from from the loop.
Right.
We got two last ha's because
it it awaits sleep one thousand before it stops laughing.
So here's a way to kind of orchestrate.
Using a few different ways of like kind of linearist,
linearly saying,
oh, sleep for this, sleep for this long.
And then do this thing.
Sleep for this long.
Or you can do a loop
of saying.
Loop for this amount that's multiple.
It's multiplied by by your iterator.
So, you know, the number can be dynamic.
That's that's why that's an example of.
While you also have this this other
thing that's running on its own beat.
This laughing this interval,
which you can start and stop.
Using the interval ID. That's LinkedIn.
That's also running on the same.
The same div.
So,
this is a not a lot going on.
It's not in here, but it's still quite a bit.
So,
the code is also available to you.
You can play around with this stuff.
You can make time-based work using just text.
You could also do this using track
elements on a sign with audio thing.
If you
were to kind of hand code all the timing.
There's a lot of ways to do work like this.
But in terms of a very simple one line text output.
It has kind of a complex sense of timing to it.
I thought this would be a good example of that.